No.
All right.
Thank you very much, Mr. Blakely, for coming along.
I think you know why we're here. We've got about half an hour
scheduled with you and half an hour with Alison McDonald.
So I invite you to... We've got your
statement and comments. I invite you to speak to that, and then I think members
have got questions, and we'll just take it from there, if it's okay.
Thank you.
Then your hands.
MB officials did not deliberately attempt to mislead the select.
We had a genuinely held belief at the time that there were commercial and
budget sensitivities that limited what could be said in a
public forum.
In hindsight, we should have taken a different approach.
We should have found a way to be clearer about the status of the project in
a public forum,
and also offered to provide secret evidence to the committee
for those issues that were truly commercial and budget sensitive.
I apologize for that.
We'll be strengthening how MB handles these select committee
proceedings, from how we prepare, to
training that we provide, through to post-hearing follow-up.
Take it seriously. Select committees are an important part of our democratic
institutions, and we take that vision of information seriously.
I would never deliberately mislead a select committee. Thank you, Mr. Chair.
Thank you. All right. Dr. Webb.
Thank you. Thank you for that statement and your letter.
Just for clarity,
you say in your letter to the Education Workforce Committee that you should've
been clearer about the status of the project.
In saying that, essentially you're saying you should've acknowledged that the
project had been brought to an end. Is that right?
Yes. The difficulty that we had at the time was that we were in the
middle of these commercial-
Yeah
... negotiations.
And so if we move on, in the same hearing, although it was
Alice McDonald's words,
to say that the project was morphing and it was taking so
long,
and the original identity of the project
has been going for some time,
you'd accept now that all those statements are not accurate.
They were incomplete. That we were trying to
convey that-
Well, okay
... there was a new approach being taken.
Yeah, we'll just let you-
But no, well, to say that
a project is still on foot
because it's taking so long suggests that it's still on foot, doesn't it?
We said in our answer that the
project would be taking a different direction.
I said that options were being looked at, and so the future of the
identity solution was changing.
Well, your words were,
"We're in the process of working out what the project looks like
going forward."
But that very project had been terminated, hadn't it?
What I was referring to was the need for an identity solution
as-
Well, were you in any doubt that Phil Twyford's question was
referring to the biometric capability upgrade?
No, I understood that, what he was referring to.
And that project had been terminated, hadn't it?
The project had not been formally terminated at that point.
Well-
The contract with NEC had been terminated, in
December.
Yeah.
The project was actually only formally closed, recently.
No. Let's be clear. The notice of termination
was given in December.
Correct.
There was a 20-day notice period which accrued into
January. So the project was terminated in January,
wasn't it?
The contract with NEC was, yes.
Right.
Okay. Now, I'm not going to ask you about post-hearing questions because I don't
think they're quite as important.
But I just do want to make it clear that both you, in your letter of 26th
June to this committee, you accept that both you and Ms.
McDonald knew, had active knowledge, that the project had been
terminated.
Let me just expand on this slightly.
We knew that the contract had been terminated.
We knew that options were being looked at for what the future
biometric identity looked like. Whether that ended up being part of the
same project or a different project was actually not known at that point.
We knew that we would not be proceeding with the current NEC
solution-
Right
... but we didn't know yet what the future solution would be.
I want to ask some questions about your
preparation for the meeting. So you were aware, and you
note this in your letter as well, that there was an item on the agenda called
Investment in New IT Systems and Paperless Applications,
weren't you?
Correct.
And you identify that there were OIA
requests that had been asked on, that touched on this topic,
active OIA requests.
Yes.
And at the time of the hearing,
a review into the project had been commissioned because it was a bit of a
disaster. That's correct as well, isn't it?
That is correct.
And the review itself identifies that you'd been
providing to the minister, a dashboard on the
project in every weekly report since mid 2025.
Yeah?
Yes.
And in fact, the ministers had received, Nicola
Willis and Erica Stanford, had received several briefings on exactly on
this project. Is that correct?
Yes.
And you're probably aware, and it crops up in weekly reports I think, that Jill
Bonnar of RNZ was pursuing this matter and
had published a couple of articles on it already.
And so you'd have to say that this was a project with a bit of
political risk given that $20,...
$30 million or more had gone into it already.
Well, I won't comment on political risk, but certainly delivery risk.
And you held, or in your, in MB's offices,
there were three preparatory sessions for the
review on 10 February, 17 February, and 3 March.
Correct.
And that doc- at that meeting, there was a document, at all three of those
meetings, called Estimates Prep. You're aware of that?
Yes.
And one of the headings in that document was
Biometric Capability Update. Is that correct?
Yes.
And I've got it here if you need me to refer to it, but one of the
questions in that,
because it was a list of possible questions that could be asked, and one of
those questions identifies the delay in that project and says, "What
happened?" Are you aware of that question?
Yes.
Right.
So this was a very problematic project with clear political
risks, so you must have discussed it at
one of those preparatory meetings. Is that correct?
No. In fact, the, as far as best as the participants in that can
remember, it didn't come up. The document that you're referring to
was potential questions that our team used
to do some Q&A during those prep sessions.
And the participants, to the best of their recollection, don't recall the BCU
questions coming up. I'm going to make a couple other points on this.
So the preparation was for a three-hour select committee.
We had a large volume of material, which you've got in
your evidence to prepare for that. We covered a whole range of issues.
In particular, in relation to that IT project, we focused a lot
on preparing for our future services, and there was a large discussion about that
at the committee. So I accept that it was an
oversight that there was no written material in our pack for
the BCU,
and that we should've covered at that session. I accept that.
So-
Just one more then.
Okay. Well-
We can come back.
Okay. Well, let me put it really clearly.
You knew this issue might be raised.
You knew the project had been terminated.
It was in your estimates prep documentation.
You'd briefed two ministers on this project.
And you're saying now
that you had not prepared for this
question to come up in a select committee estimates hearing.
At the time, I understood, Allison understood, that there were
budget and commercial sensitivities that limited what we could say.
Well, no. This is it. This is the question.
I've given all of that background and the political heat
on this question. Are you going to say to this committee now
you had not prepared that this question would
come up in committee?
We were clearly not adequately prepared.
I had, to my recollection, I had a brief conversation with
Allison that if it came up, that she would take the lead,
and that both of us, well, that wasn't part of the conversation, but both of us
understood that at the time there were these sensitivities.
So you had prepared. You'd had a conversation with
Allison about this very issue.
To my recollection, yes.
And you decided because of commercial sensitivities,
you wouldn't
tell the committee that the project had been terminated.
There was no active decision the way you're describing.
I understood at the time that there were these sensitivities.
I didn't interrogate those,
and I should have. I accepted the position that it
precluded what could be said, and that Official Information Act request that you
refer to shows that at the time, MB considered that those were sensitive enough
to be withheld in that OIA release.
Okay. I think what we're all struggling with is
Phil Twyford asks,
"Tell us about the key risks in milestones and implementation,
milestones, whether any milestones have slipped."
And,
but basically,
at the time he asked that,
the ministry had formally terminated the contract for the BCU project,
and actually that basically happened in October.
Well, it started in October, but it was certainly done by the end of December
2025, early 2026. And so
the hearing's in March, and so it's dead. Like, it's finished.
So what are we missing here? Why didn't you just say that?
I agree. We got it wrong. I accept that, and we should've said it
differently. As I said, at the time, we were concerned that
talking about that publicly-
Yeah
Make it difficult to conclude the commercial negotiations.
We were in negotiations about the final payment with NEC.
Right.
We'd started in different positions on that.
We knew those were still live. In fact, those weren't concluded until the 15th of
June. We were worried that if that played out in a public forum,
that might make it more difficult to conclude those.
Was also in the budget process. Take budget sensitivity-
Yeah
... seriously. The write-off was subject to that going through the budget process.
Yeah.
So what we were, at the time, worried about was moving
into termination-
Yes
... would bring all of that out.
Yes.
Now, I accept we should've taken a different approach, but that was our thinking at
the time.
You could've gone to a secret hearing.
I accept that.
You know.
And as I say, we were under-prepared to think through these different
eventualities.
Okay. I don't want to take up too much more time.
We'll go, Scott first-
Yeah
... then Parmjeet, then-
Look
... Ricardo.
Thanks, Mr. Chair. I want to just come back to the point that Dr.
Webb was making about the prep meetings that took place.
So there were three prep meetings, and
in the notes that were provided, this matter was clearly highlighted,
although you say not discussed. Is that correct?
That's my reflection, and that's the reflection of others who have asked it.
But you've also told us today that a decision had
been made, either individually or collectively, that to discuss these
matters was problematic because of perceived commercial
sensitivities.
I don't think it was an active decision.
It was an understanding that both of us had that there were these sensitivities in
play that limited what we could say.
So what I'm trying to get at is, how was that
view formed, and at what point?
Hmm.
And why? Because as the chairman has said, there's
ample provision for select committee proceedings to be heard in
secret.
And as a senior public servant, I would have assumed, as I think most of us
sitting around the table, that that would be kind of
muscle memory knowledge that you and she would
have had.
So there was
no active decision, to answer in this way, and I think that that was a
failing in our preparation. Had there been a written material
as part of that pack, you can see there's like an 80-page prep pack.
Yeah.
But it doesn't include BCU. If it had, that would've
been the process of creating those,
there would've been interrogation about what was appropriate to say and not say.
Yeah.
So there wasn't an active decision.
I was aware of the negotiations. The team had briefed me on where
those were up to, which is why it was in our minds.
Yeah.
But to your last point,
you're right. We should've asked for secret.
It's not something that I had seen happen before in a estimates
annual review hearing, so it wasn't in my consciousness, and it wasn't something
that I was
easily aware that I could take advantage of.
So I accept that I should've been knowledgeable about that.
But at some point, somebody thought this matter
was significantly important enough to include in the prep
notes
that were for the three prep meetings that were held.
And given the honorable Phil Twyford's
OIAs and the questions that he had been asking pre
the hearing,
I would have thought that that would have been a sufficient flag to
raise with your colleagues that, hey, this is something we should be thinking
about carefully rather than just, frankly, ad-libbing on the day.
I agree with you, and
as I say, it's surprising in hindsight that there's
no written material on BC that shows that we weren't well enough prepared, and I
accept that.
How many prep meetings have you had for this meeting today?
I'm not sure. Several.
Several. Were there prep notes prepared for this meeting today?
Yes. Well, and I've got my whole, my full pack here of evidence that-
Can you table the prep notes for this meeting today at some stage, please?
I don't know if that's necessarily-
Well, I'm keen to know, because I think that Dr.
Webb's been asking a series of questions about what prep work was
done ahead of the select committee hearing, and it's clear that
there is a pattern of prep meetings being held.
Don't have a problem with that. But I'm keen to know what gets prepped,
what doesn't, who decides-
Okay
...
and what are the potential answers that are prepped for.
Well, we can get into the prep for the prep.
I don't know if that's-
Well, that's kind of where we're at.
Well, let's just see how the hearing's going. Come back to that.
No, we'll get Parmjeet first, and then Ricardo, then-
So thank you. So first I want to confirm that you are saying that there were no
discussions within MBIE about whether the committee should be
informed of cancellation of this project or not.
So there were no discussions, that's what you're saying?
That's right. There was no active decision.
Yeah.
That's correct.
All right. So there was nobody who advised against providing that
information to the select committee. That's what you're saying?
That's right.
Okay.
Because, yes, that's right.
Yeah. So after your hearing in March,
your staff would have seen what was said in the select committee,
and there must be some reactions from seeing what was
disclosed to the select committee.
And you had some time to come back to the select committee after that
period. I want to hear what were the discussions
that happened for what you said in the select committee in March,
and then why MBIE didn't come back to the
select committee until the point it was disclosed by the
minister.
So there weren't any discussions afterwards.
We
felt that we'd answered the questions as best we could, given the
limitations that we were under. So it wasn't until
the honorable Phil Twyford
raised the concerns after June that I then had
a chance to realize that we should've taken a different approach.
It wasn't that we deliberately did something
that we then discussed. It was, we never had any
intentions to mislead. It's actually very common for public servants to have
to be aware of what is sensitive and can't be revealed in a public
forum, cabinet decision-making processes, budget sensitivities.
That is common-
To be able to answer questions as best you can within limitations, and that's what
we felt we were doing. I accept that we should've taken a different approach, but
there was never any intention to mislead.
So if honorable Phil Twyford didn't raise that issue,
you would not have revealed that the information disclosed to the Select Committee
was not complete and accurate?
Well, when there are sensitivities,
they cease to become sensitive once decisions are made and
things
are then released. And so, in this case, once those
negotiations had concluded, once the budget process is concluded, then that
would've been an obvious time to be able to release
those.
So who is responsible to ensure that the Select Committee is provided
complete and accurate information?
Well, all officials
preparing information for committees, and then ultimately who signs off on
responses to committees have the responsibility to ensure that the information is
accurate.
So everybody in that group was happy with the information that was provided
to the Select Committee. That's what you say?
So you were happy with the information that was provided to the Select Committee,
given
the answer that you have provided.
At the time, I didn't think I'd done anything wrong.
I thought I was answering the question as best I could given the limitations
that we had.
So who had put the limitations? You had put the limitations, right?
Well,
yes. We
felt that there were these commercial and budget sensitivities.
There were live negotiations. There was a live budget
initiative.
And as per the Official Information Act, which was also live at that
point, we felt that information shouldn't be released in the public
forum. And so that's what we had in our minds at the time.
And I accept that that was the wrong approach.
Yeah. You're not new to appearing before Select Committees.
No.
And are you saying that you were not aware that you could write to the Select
Committee before the hearing that you would require a private session?
I guess I'm saying
yes. It wasn't something that was clear to me
that I could avail myself of. I've been to a lot of these, and I've never
seen that in annual review estimates before, and I accept that
I should've known that, but that wasn't something that was clear in my mind.
Is there something else of similar nature that you have presented to the
Select Committee which might be an issue
so far to any Select Committee that you've appeared before?
I always try and answer the questions as best I can within
where there might be sensitivities, and often those will
end with if something subject to cabinet processes.
Then once those decisions are made, then ministers would announce them.
Once budget sensitivities have gone, they'd be in the budget.
And similarly for commercial. I've always tried to answer as
best I can.
That's not very satisfying actually because that creates a doubt in our mind that
maybe there was something-
Pardon me. Is the-
Yeah
... the history-
Yes, Mr. Chair
Past stuff's not super relevant.
Riccardo.
Well, we are trying to determine if this was deliberate or not.
Is this the only instance-
Yeah
... in which you were asked for information about the project in which you were not
forthcoming?
So this was the only time that I've been
in the chair
for this project apart from June hearing.
Minister?
Well, I can't speak for the minister.
All right. Well, the other question I had then, if we can move on then, if you
can't answer to that,
was why couldn't you have told us that the project had ended without disclosing,
for example, the amount of the socialized write-off that would've been commercially
sensitive? Do you accept that perhaps you could have at least
revealed to us that the project had terminated without revealing commercially
sensitive information?
Yeah. I absolutely accept that we should've taken a different approach.
There was many things we could've said that stopped short of revealing those
sensitivities, and I accept that
we got that wrong.
But if
you have leaned on the fact that one of the reasons you didn't provide the
information was that it was commercially sensitive and it had budget implications,
why are you also accepting that you could have revealed to us the project had
terminated without revealing those commercially sensitive details?
Well, I'm not sure I would've
said that.
Right.
I think there are different ways we could've said it.
For example, we could've said
that we could've sought for secret information.
We could've been clear that the current solution was not continuing,
stopping short of talking about...
Perhaps we could've even said, and this is in hindsight, we should've
taken legal advice about attesting that.
There are a number of ways we could've said it, including offering for secret
evidence, and I accept that we should've been better prepared to do so.
And without you telling us that you had received advice or sought
advice around what you could actually reveal to us,
what assurances can you give us that the commercially sensitive argument wasn't
just an afterthought?
Well,
I think one of the best
tests for that is the fact that there was an Official Information Act request that
was released later in March that withheld the information
on the grounds of commercial sensitivity.
That's how MB considered at the time, that that
information-
But the OIA was asking probably more than just simply whether the project had
terminated or otherwise, right? The question at the Select Committee was just the
state of the project, not the commercially sensitive data.
So to compare an OIA that would've been asking for far more information
as a sort of a parallel to not revealing the status of the project, do you not see
how that actually is not a comparable thing to bring up?
But your question was how do we know that that's what you thought at the time, and
I'm giving you this was a release that happened at a very similar time
where MB took a similar approach to trying to protect those
sensitivities. So I accept that we
got it wrong, but at the time it was a genuinely held belief that we
needed to protect those sensitivities.
Which of the sensitivities were included in the honorable Phil Twyford's questions?
I think as soon as we get into terminating
contracts, I think in our minds at the time we were worried that that was bound up
with-
The commercial negotiations which were underway.
And as I say, we were in different places with the vendor.
That was a live conversation about what the final payment would be.
Can I have one more question?
Yeah.
So
you've got this document, which is your estimates prep document, a list of
possible questions. And then you've got a number of other documents, one of
which is this 80-page material for hearing
attendees, which basically tracks all of the
estimates prepped and gives the answers,
except for the biometric capability update section.
It's just the one thing that's missing.
Right.
Did you
intentionally leave that out for the very
reasons you've given, that you didn't think you could really
talk about it in committee, it was sensitive?
I don't believe so.
I don't know why there wasn't material in there, but the team has looked back,
and in fact, there was no BCU item for the
last several
hearing packs going back. So again, that seems
surprising. But it wasn't just this committee hearing.
There's slight dollar grade.
I accept that.
The project was a disaster. The fact that no one bothered to prepare to explain why
it was a disaster, sort of
it's both terrible and good for you-
I do agree
... bad for the public service.
Yeah. Absolutely.
Okay. I think that's it.
There have been OIO requests from a-
Yeah
... parliament.
Well, it's so un-past remarkable that this project was just, oh, you know, it
beggars belief.
Is there a reason, any reason it wasn't in there, given
this background that Mr. Bishop's outlined?
I do not know why there wasn't any material in there.
Oh.
Mr. Chair, if I may. If the intent wasn't to
deliberately mislead Parliament, why didn't you proactively seek
to clarify to the committee following post-hearing questions where the sort of
status of the project was very specifically identified?
Well,
I accept we should have done that differently.
At the time, we thought we were answering the questions as best we could
within those constraints. So, but I accept that we've got that wrong.
But did you actually, in drafting the post-hearing questions,
seek advice or consider the commercial sensitivity, or was it just something
that you both just kind of nod your head and
didn't really discuss with anyone else?
I was not involved in the sign-out process for the post-hearing
question. And that is something-
Do you know who was and whether the commercially sensitive components were factored
in in the drafting of the reply?
I believe that the
new acting Deputy Secretary for Immigration signed those out, but she'd only been
in the role for a week since Alison had-
That's my question, was whether the commercially sensitive components-
Yes
... factored into the reply.
Yes.
That was, I thought from a question that was straightforward.
Yeah, the first part was who signed it out.
The second part, I'm not aware, I don't know whether there was
assurances sought. I suspect not. But I don't know that for sure.
Okay. We've got a few minutes left. Susan's been patiently waiting, then we'll go.
Okay. Just following on from my colleague, Honorable Scott Simpson's
questions before and Honorable Duncan Webb, I just want to be really
clear. So you had the three meetings where you were briefed about the estimates
hearings, and you don't recall discussing at any point during that time about the
biometric capability update. So I just want to be really
clear, was it an active omission not to include the
biometric-
No
... in the-
No, absolutely not. It was never a deliberate decision.
It was never discussed. It was never a deliberate decision.
Yeah, and
the context here, which you can see from some of the material that we provided, is
that there had been different SROs in place for
senior responsible officers.
There were changes in personnel. There are a number of contextual factors,
but that's no excuse.
But there was no deliberate
decision.
Of a $30 million project.
Parmjeet and then Ricardo, then we'll-
I've just got a-
So the way you have explained it, it makes me think that every time you appear
before the select committee for any hearing, we should be asking you if you're
giving your responses within some constraint so that we know if there are any
constraints and you're not revealing accurate or complete
information. Are you suggesting that that's what select committee should be doing?
No. As officials, we should be clear when there are-
Yeah
... constraints that we're operating within.
Yeah.
And
usually, I would've thought that I would say that.
I would say, "That would be subject to ministers or cabinet decisions," or I'd be
saying, "That's subject to budget decisions."
That that is what select committee should expect.
That if there are constraints, then officials are revealing when there are
constraints about what they can say, and that's the approach that we should have
taken. And then also offering to do
evidence in secret as well.
Yeah. And you can see because of this how select committees can
find it really hard to trust answers that are provided in
select committees. So how are you going to rebuild confidence
going forward?
Well, we have to rebuild confidence by providing complete
answers to you and demonstrating-
How do we know it?
Well, we will be strengthening our processes.
I'll be putting in training for-- We already have training for officials
appearing before select committees for bills, but not for hearings.
We'll be adding that. So we will strengthen our processes, and then we just have to
demonstrate that when we're providing you with information that you get
the complete as possible.
Okay, one final one from Ricardo then-
Yeah, just thinking of other opportunities that you would have had to sort of
clarify this on. Answers to question 84,
you noted that reviews were routine operational activity, and you didn't think
to disclose the Greg James review on what went wrong.
Then on the correspondence, you've noticed that- We could also advise on item
84 that some reviews are for the minister only.
Do you not think that even that kind of exchange
signals that perhaps there was information you could have revealed to us or
considered giving to us but didn't?
And what made MBIE not pause and think that perhaps the answers we were getting
were just simply not forthright or sufficient at that point?
So again, I wasn't involved directly in those, but I think at the time,
MB officials felt that those sensitivities were in play, and so they
again gave information while
not revealing what was subject to sensitivities.
And I accept that we got that wrong and that we should have taken the time
to reflect on those post-hearing questions.
And that's why I want to make sure that all of those post-hearing questions
where there are specific sensitivities like this are being escalated to all the
relevant people, including me.
Okay. Thank you very much. Appreciate your time.
We will come back to you if required.
You are free to go.
Now Alison's on Zoom, is she? Or Teams or whatever
program we use.
Hello, can you hear me?
Awesome.
She's on mute, I think.
You're on mute, are they? Can you hear me?
She's not on mute. I think her audio's not connected.
So you may want to check the bottom left of your corner where the microphone is and
just check that the right audio device is-
Yeah
... there's a little arrow next to your mic which will show you.
Could be that a Bluetooth
speaker is connected.
Good, we have a technical expert.
I've got expertise.
It was remarkably, you're straight into it, Ricardo.
Yeah.
It's happened a few times.
Not with her, but-
No.
How's that? Can you hear me?
Oh, no.
We had it briefly.
Okay.
Let's go back again. That's
it.
Did you guys test this before?
No.
Yeah. It's not on this side.
Oh.
It's probably, I'd reckon it's-
Can you hear me now?
Yes, yes. Hello.
Sorry about that.
It's okay. Thank you.
Hey, thank you for your time. We've just had
Mr. Blakely from MBIE in.
Alison, we've got about half an hour with
you, if that's okay, Ms. McDonald.
Yep.
So to let you know why we're here,
we just heard from
Nick Blakely.
So we've got, I don't know if you can see all the members here, you probably...
Can she see everyone here? She probably can.
She can see the people at the bottom.
Oh, she can see the people at the bottom. Okay.
Well, we've got
Parmjeet Parmar, Jamie Arbuckle, Suze Redmayne, Honorable Scott Simpson,
Honorable Dr. Duncan Webb, Preston McConnell and Ricardo Menendez March.
So we'll start with Duncan and we'll just go around the room like we did before.
I'd like to hear from Alison first.
Oh, sorry. Yes. Sorry. My apologies. Yes.
Invite you to, we've got
the statement. We invite you to say a few words and then we'll take some questions.
Thank you. Thank you for the opportunity to talk to you, this morning for
me, this evening for you.
I retired after 41 years of public service in April this year,
and throughout my career I prided myself on my integrity and my commitment to
serving the public and governments of all colors.
At the Education and Workforce Select Committee hearing, one of the numerous
questions covering a really wide range of topics was about the ministry's identity
system upgrade.
I attempted to explain to the committee that alternative options to the identity
program were being looked at without actually referring or referencing the
cessation of the IT contract, which I had been told could not be discussed.
Although I'm not directly or was not directly involved in the commercial
discussions or the preparation of the budget bid relating to the biometric
capability IT project, I understood that neither could be
discussed publicly.
On reflection, the reference to milestone slippage in the
question asked of us should've triggered a much more targeted response
about the IT project that was within the identity program.
The IT project had clearly not delivered to the milestone set, which was part of
the reason that I'd recommended to the acting CE at the time that we consider a
different solution for this aspect of the identity program.
I am really sorry that I missed this in the heat of
questioning. And although we wouldn't have been able to talk about the
cessation of the IT contract publicly, as Nick acknowledged
previously, MB could have found a way to brief the committee separately.
Throughout my career as a public servant, I've worked hard to support the
advancement of transparent government.
I've acknowledged both in my written response to the committee and again today that
MB's response to this question was wanting, and I apologize to the committee for
that. However, I'd like to take this opportunity to assure the committee that
I had no intention whatsoever to mislead the select committee, and I find
the suggestion that I might have acted deliberately to mislead Parliament extremely
distressing. Thank you.
Well, thank you for that. I think all of us heard you
say you were told it couldn't be discussed.
That's right. Mm-hmm.
Who told you that?
And when?
There were a number of times throughout the commercially insensitive
negotiations that I was told I couldn't talk to anyone about it, other than the
minister and the people who were aware within MB, which was a very limited
number of people.
Was the ministry-
Yeah. Sorry, rather than just have a free for all, we'll go Dr. Webb first.
I think you'll get the same line of questions.
Okay. I did hear that Um.
Mm-hmm.
So it makes sense then that
the status of the project wasn't in any of the
kind of hearing packs that's given-
Mm
... to a wide group of people.
Mm.
Was that left out of the hearing packs
because it was a commercially sensitive matter that you could only speak
to with a small group of people?
I don't know for sure because I wasn't involved in the preparation, but I would
expect that my team wouldn't have questioned it for that reason.
Okay.
I'm not sure if you heard Nick Blakeley's evidence just now.
Were you-
Yes, I did.
Okay.
Yes, I did. Yeah.
So Nick Blakeley said that he had a conversation with you about
the biometric capability upgrade in respect-
Mm
... of this annual review.
Mm.
In that conversation, did you discuss the
fact, either of you, that you couldn't be
fulsome with the committee about it?
Well, we discussed that we knew we couldn't talk publicly about the
commercial sensitivity or the IT project at all, and that's
why,
as I say, in hindsight it
should've been more targeted around the IT project, but I talked about the wider
program, trying to indicate to the committee that we were looking at
something different without actually saying we'd canceled the IT project.
That my intention was actually to
give more information without giving away commercial sensitivities.
Yeah.
Because we've got your words. I've got your words in front of us.
Mm-hmm.
The original identity program has been going for some time,
and I guess-
Mm
... the point being that that's inconsistent with it not going because it had
been terminated, right? And you accept that now, I think.
Well, the IT project, yes, but the program was ongoing and we were talking
to DIA about what we do. I'm
not trying to be cute, I'm just talking about how I had framed it in my mind at the
time.
And I guess would it be fair to say that pre the estimates hearing, either
in that conversation with Nick Blakeley or otherwise-
Mm-hmm
... you had essentially thought, "How am I going to manage this if I get asked?"
Yes, I had. I'd thought, "How do I give the committee as much information
as I can without revealing things that I was aware I
couldn't talk about?" So I had, and that is the answer I
gave. And I admit now,
on reflection with hindsight,
that I might have paused and thought.
But when I think about how... And I looked at the footage again, obviously,
before coming to this committee. It was quite a
fast-moving, wide-ranging committee, and even when we stopped on that line of
questioning, we moved on quickly, and Nick had said we'll follow up, and in my mind
once we follow up, we will follow up with whatever we can when we
can. That's always been my experience.
So it didn't
register with me, if you'd like to go any further.
No, but you always knew that... Because one of the estimates prep
questions is, there's been a delay.
Mm.
What's happened?
You always knew that in response to that question, you weren't going to
say, "It's been terminated." Would that be right?
Yes. And in the prep sessions,
the vast majority of people in the prep sessions wouldn't have known about what was
happening with the IT project either.
Did you mention this biometric project in the prep
sessions?
I don't recall.
Okay.
And I think I would recall if we did because I would've found it quite difficult,
with no one in the room knowing what was going on. So.
Okay.
Scott.
Well, thank you, and thank you for your time.
Conscious that it's early morning for you, but-
Mm
... we appreciate you being with us.
Of course.
You heard
Nick Blakeley's
submission to this committee only a few minutes ago.
Yeah.
And I want to test this situation
regarding
who knew what when.
Mm.
And you've made it clear in your submission to us
today that you had been told on more than one occasion, multiple
occasions,
that you couldn't talk about this program because
it was commercially sensitive. So there were prep notes
prepared that included this subject, and yet both
you and Mr. Blakeley say that there was
no prep discussion about it, and yet several prep
meetings were held.
Mm.
I just find that kind of very difficult to-
Mm
... correlate with questions that the honorable
Phil Twyford had been asking in writing to MV,
that had been the subject of answers to the OIA questions he had been
raising, and yet this wasn't part of
a professional prep program for a select
committee hearing
of the Parliament of New Zealand,
where members can, I think, expect to
be given honest, frank, and fulsome
answers. I just have difficulty correlating
those, what was answered on the, what was in the transcript, what you said at
the select committee, and the prep work that was or wasn't done.
And I'm interested to know a bit more about who told you when and what, why.
And in what format.
Yeah. And in what format. It's a
long-winded way of saying, who knew what when.
Yes. Okay. So
I think
in my mind the program had not stopped.
Well, it hadn't stopped, it had carried on going.
The IT project was one element of the identity program.
And we had done a lot of preparation around our future services, which is the big
IT
overhaul piece, if you like, for Immigration New Zealand.
The biometric capability IT project wasn't
managed by me or Immigration New Zealand.
It was managed by another part of MV.
And so
all I was aware of, I was in some of the conversations with the
CE and others. I was in one of the ministerial
conversations about it. But I really did not know any of the
detail about it. And had there-
Had we been able to talk about the IT project, I wouldn't have been the person
talking to it either. It would've been the deputy secretary who knew about the
project and was responsible for it.
So for me, I prepped on everything that was my responsibility.
It's my responsibility as the Deputy Secretary for Immigration New Zealand, it was
my responsibility to make sure that whatever IT slotted into the immigration
identity program and landed well.
But other than that, I just was on the side of
conversations that said things were
commercially sensitive. I knew there was a budget bid
being proposed and it's a
fundamental piece that's drummed into you from day one as a public servant, that
you don't talk about anything in the budget publicly.
And so that's really the context I can give you.
But sorry to interrupt. If you basically had nothing to do with it, why were we
asked three questions about it?
Well-
Why don't we just get somebody else of the cast of thousands who wouldn't have been
asked the questions?
Well, I think the thing at the time, the deputy secretary responsible had just
gone. The deputy secretary before that had gone before them.
The chief executive, Nick, had only just started acting.
And I honestly thought I was trying to help the committee understand that we were
moving in a different direction. On reflection, that was the wrong thing to do.
Yeah. Well, that's definitely true.
At one point you said
the
program was morphemed-
Mm
... exploring a better all-of-government solution.
That was true.
Well, sort of.
That is true.
That's sort of true. The program was dead at that point. You'd canceled a contract.
You'd written off-
No, the IT-
... near about 30 million bucks of taxpayer cash.
Would've been good if you'd said that
The IT project was in the process of being closed at that time, but the
program was ongoing.
Yes.
We run an identity program,
and we need to upgrade it. That was carrying on.
So you're basically drawing a distinction between the IT bit of the
identity program. Is that like a subset of the identity thing?
Yes. Yes.
But Mr. Blakely, can I put to you, Mr.
Blakely, I put to him very clearly that it was obvious that the
question from Phil Twyford was about the
biometric capability upgrade-
And the post questions
... that had been terminated, and he responded to that question, yes,
that we knew that's what this line of questioning was about.
Did you think it was about the wider identity project, or did you-
Well, I did
... think it was about the biometric capability upgrade?
I actually did. Yes.
You're right. You're right. Yeah.
And as I
said in my answer, I actually did think that was the case, and on reflection,
and when he said the word milestones, I really should've stopped and thought,
and then said that there were issues with the IT program that we were
working through or something that would've been an indicator that then
follow up with a different approach to the committee.
But I honestly, at the time, was trying to help say that
we were going in a different direction.
Okay.
Well, Ricardo then Panji, then Tracy hasn't had one yet.
I hear your point that at the time you thought it was about the broader identity
program. But once we got post-hearing questions, and I specifically refer to
63 and 84, those were very specifically on the sort of BCU.
Did the person signing these answers off had any knowledge
of where the program was at, and did you sort of have any
oversight or got to see the answers whatsoever?
No, I had left by then.
And secondly-
Sorry, in addition,
if I may, had I been there, I would've insisted they were signed off
by the person responsible. I wouldn't have signed them off.
Not because I didn't agree with them, and to be honest, I'm not sure I've seen
them. I probably have them somewhere in these papers.
But
the person who was acting, obviously.
So who exactly was told? Was it just you and Nick that you couldn't
discuss this program? You mentioned that there were multiple times.
Was it just you and Nick, or-
No. All of the people involved. So, within my team,
the general manager who ran the identity program was aware.
The previous CE obviously was aware.
The previous acting CE was aware, and the previous two deputy secretaries who were
involved in the negotiations for the IT contract were aware.
And outside of that, I wasn't party to anyone else.
There was a project manager who would've been aware, who's no longer in the
ministry.
And I think that really would be about it.
That's kind of where I was-
But you-
... limited, sir, at the way we were
... do you not think there's a disconnect, though, between what you're telling us
right now and what the prep notes actually sort of show?
Because I find it weird that this is not so explicitly noted in the
preparatory notes. If this was something that you'd been told multiple times that
you could not actually speak about-
Yeah, I understand
... why is that not reflected in the preparatory notes?
Because that would make it really easy-
I can't answer that. Sorry, I don't know. I don't know why that wasn't in there.
But as I say, it didn't ring any bells with me that there wasn't anything in there
because we were in the midst of negotiations, or the
department was. Yeah.
And
did at any point
in the post-hearing questions, did you thought that perhaps you would need to seek
further advice on how you may communicate or perhaps
even reflected that at the time the answers that you gave were not
forthcoming? Like, did it not occur to you at any point after the hearing and
during the post-hearing question session that perhaps the answers that were given
were not satisfactory?
No, it really didn't. It didn't.
And I'm sorry for that. As I said, it was a very fast-moving, well, you
were there, it was a fast-moving, wide-ranging set of issues, and I
knew that MBIE was going to follow up on it, and that's where I left it, and I
trusted that that would happen.
What does this say about the organization, then?
MBIE is an organization that does the
best it can
To serve the public and the government of the day.
And no one will have done this with ill intent. I can say that for sure.
It's a very proud public service organization where people work really hard every
day to deliver for New Zealand, and nothing that either
Nick, myself, or anyone in any of our teams would've done would've been trying to
mislead.
Okay. All right. Parmjeet, and then Suz, and then... Oh, sorry.
I did say Parmjeet, then Tracy.
Yeah.
Parmjeet.
Yes. I heard you saying that you were told that this is commercially
sensitive, so you can't disclose this information in a public hearing.
Mm.
Who advised you that?
Well, I think it was mentioned in the meetings that I had been
party to. And I mean, the fact even when we briefed the minister,
it was only ever the CE who was in the room or the CE and a
deputy secretary. The teams did not know what was being
disclosed because everything was so commercially sensitive at the time.
But then who advised that-
And I can't tell you why, because I wasn't in the discussions
You-
So who advised you that you cannot discuss that
in a public hearing?
So that advice from somewhere you think?
Well, it could not be discussed publicly, that's-
Mm
... I mean, there were two parts to it.
One, the commercial negotiations, which for my whole career, I've always been
told could not be discussed publicly until concluded.
Two, was the budget bid, which was sensitive, and throughout
my career I've never discussed anything that's within a budget bid.
No, I understand that.
And
Who advised you in this case? In this case, who
advised you that this cannot be discussed in a public hearing?
It would've been within conversations with the previous CE and deputy secretary.
I mean, it has to be somebody you would listen to, right?
It can't be just random meeting conversation and you would agree-
Yes.
That would've been where the discussions were held, with those people, yes.
And also the fact in 41 years, I had never been able to talk about anything where
there were commercial negotiations or a sensitive budget bid.
So-
All right. So other than this, so
you could have easily said in the select committee hearing that it's commercially
sensitive and you're not prepared to talk about this in a public hearing.
Instead of giving those answers which you gave, it would have been like a-
Yeah
... shorter answer.
As I said, on reflection if I'd have paused a bit in a
very fast-paced meeting, if I'd have paused a bit and thought about the word
milestones, then yes, I could've done, but I honestly was talking
about the wider project program, and I was honestly trying
to give a steer to what would be coming to the committee when
we did change the project. So and I am really sorry that I
didn't stop and do that in the heat of the moment, but I didn't.
In your 41 years as a public servant, how many select
committee appearances for estimates or annual
reviews or other committees did you appear in front of?
Appear as a panelist, probably just the ones in New
Zealand. I would always have been in the background in the United Kingdom.
So and
within that, I think only the ones while I was Deputy Secretary for Immigration.
Okay.
So a few, probably. Tracy.
Yes. Yeah.
Yeah.
Over four years, so that would've been about eight. Yes. Yeah.
Thank you. Mr. Blakeley said that it was
agreed that should the identity program come up in
a wide-ranging discussion,
that you would take the lead in answering that.
When it became clear to you
that it was about the BCU and not the identity
program specifically,
if you had have thought,
who would you have
asked to answer that question? Who would you have turned around to,
to seek-
I would've turned around to the deputy secretary responsible for the IT in the
organization. But he had resigned a matter of
months before, and there was somebody acting in that post, so.
But that's who I would've turned to,
had I clocked it that's what it was.
Yeah.
And given that he had resigned, and therefore it was
known that there wouldn't be anybody
suitable available to answer that
question, was that why it was decided that you would
be the person answering the question?
Mm. I don't recall us saying that I would be the lead, but I had
assumed that Nick or I would answer it, yes.
Okay.
Scott's got one more, then Suz, then Ricardo, then we'll...
One
Oh, okay. One more each. Okay. Scott, quickly.
Mine's just a quick one. Mr. Blakeley indicated
that there had been several prep meetings for today's meeting.
Did you participate in those prep meetings?
No, I did not.
Thank you.
Suz, quickly.
You were just going back to what couldn't be discussed.
I just wonder, because of commercial and budget sensitivities, did you
seek or receive a legal opinion from any...
Was that any of the discussion that transpired in respect of you not
discussing anything?
No. Because I wasn't involved in negotiations, I didn't even know who from legal
would be involved, so no, I didn't.
No.
You mentioned that one of the parties that you could've communicated this to
was the minister. Were you forthcoming with the minister
in providing that information? Because that to me also-
Yes
... lives for you.
Yeah. In the meetings that I was party to, I was
always gave free and frank advice to this minister as I have
to every minister.
Parmjeet, final question.
Very final question. So, of course there are lots of commercial
deals that happen. So,
for you to decide that this was commercially sensitive, where that advice
came from?
That would've been... It was part of the discussions and I do know that that was
said to minister as well, that we're going through commercial in confidence
conversations. So I heard it several times.
So what is the threshold for it to be decided as commercially sensitive?
So you need to be
in negotiations that might jeopardize
public funds, essentially, and that was what I understood was the case
here. So the negotiations had to be done to close.
There was a dispute definitely between the provider and MV on
what had been delivered and how workable the solution was.
And so there was a discussion, I don't know the detail of it because I wasn't party
to it, about
final payment and cessation of the project.
But about the public funds, we were told that you can't recover those public funds,
so I don't understand what you're saying here.
No. So if they were asking for more, then we had to-
Commercially sensitive only because
there were public funds involved.
But we were told-
No, it was commercially sensitive because it was a commercial contract, and there
are a number of things-
There are so many commercial contracts. But how do you decide it?
What is the threshold here?
Well, she's right about that. There was a contract in place, which they were-
Yeah. But then if she's talking about the public funds involved, we were told that
they couldn't recover those public funds. So, I don't understand.
No, I
don't know for sure, but my assumption was that the provider was asking for
more money than we had got permission from Cabinet to spend.
That was my assumption. But I really wasn't involved in the detail.
Okay. You've been pretty clear on that.
Okay, I'm going to close it off because we've got to do a post-match.
Thank you very much for your time. Where are you at the moment, in the UK?
I'm in the UK, yeah. I'll be back-
Where in the UK?
... next month. Chichester on the South Coast.
Lovely part of the world.
Nice.
Thank you very much for your time. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Thank you. Thank you.